Okay, my name is Kate Latham. I'm an assistant professor from Virginia Commonwealth University in Richmond, Virginia.
With me is Christian Settle, a former student of mine, recent graduate and independent contractor in 3D design.
A little bit about our department specifically, our current cohort is about this size currently.
So we have 200 merchandising students, 100 design students, and 97 merchandising minors.
We also have two additional, including myself, so three total accredited academic CLO instructors.
And we are one of the first schools to begin
implementing this new badge that CLO is giving out.
So any student who graduates the CLO course with an 86 average and above will receive this badge that they can then share on LinkedIn and any platform that they need exposure.
I'd like to start off, before I explain the breakdown of the course that I teach,
by talking a little bit about the course.
A little bit of why students need to know about 3D, why it's so important, and why they should be prioritizing it in their lives.
Everybody already knows the sustainability part. That's a given. That's an obvious factor of it.
It cuts down time and waste, cost, everything.
But in addition to that, you sort of want some practical information to give them to get them excited about this.
So we have seen, and the numbers are a little bit hard to come across,
but currently, from the most recent assessments by different sources,
almost half of a survey of 60 luxury brands have claimed to begin incorporating technology like AR and VR into their marketing,
and other parts of their production.
We also have a 30% rate of fashion brands having started implementing 3D processes in their production processes.
In addition to that, something really tangible for students to sort of take in is that there are over 1,400 job listings currently that relate to 3D apparel design.
And that was across four different platforms for job listings.
And if you think about it, that's in comparison to the 2,100 that is estimated in annual job opening in this field.
So that's a large percentage of those job openings.
That's pretty encouraging and a really good reason to become proficient in 3D.
Thank you.
So my teaching approach is as such.
It ultimately breaks down into what I call exercises in the classroom.
And that's a very structured step-by-step process where we go through certain tools and functions in the software.
And it's very criteria-based.
We submit screenshots of the work at different stages so I can check it off.
And we move into project-based learning.
So how do we start to apply these tools and these functions in a project setting?
And we also try to talk, encourage other softwares that can supplement CLO, like Blender.
Obviously, Adobe Programming.
Adobe programs like Illustrator and Photoshop are going to help.
And then really powerful programs like Unreal Engine.
The more specific breakdown of what I like to focus on in my teaching, I'll start with the interface and navigation.
The student needs to know how to get around the program first and foremost.
Then we go into tools.
We like to focus on tools in the order that they are relevant in a work process for a creative individual, specifically for fashion.
We also focus on garment production.
So these tools will then feed into patterning and actually building the garment.
And each garment is going to require different tools and different know-hows, different processes and operations.
So it sort of compounds after each garment that we do.
Simultaneously, we are developing our creative concept for that project-based learning where they will begin to do research on target demographics.
They'll create a persona.
And then build an entire concept to pull designs.
In the end of the course, we focus on advanced techniques.
So high-quality renders of still shots, but also animation.
So we bring in motion files.
And again, we talk about those softwares that are going to really supplement the program, like Daz for creating new avatars, custom avatars, Blender.
And...
And the...
And the content that we thought we were going to leave on a page.
So that was going to be the Violet class, where we started data analytics.
We started a project.
We looked at that across a range of different styles.
We started with custom
...
tools and operations that are going to give them the best understanding of how to use
this in a real-world scenario, in their own individual design processes or under an employer.
So the workflow of our four-month semester, you can see at the bottom, I've broken it into four
months. And that first month, we are going through exercise through seven pretty much.
We have a discussion for these first two months.
I break it down. It roughly happens once in a month. And in these discussions, I like to
talk about AI. A good one to discuss as a class is ethics, of course, and how we should be using
AI and technologies that are coming into our sort of disposal now and how we should be thinking of AI
and how we should be using it as creatives. We also work on our personas or character profiles,
depending on the final prompt that we do for that semester. And you see in month two,
we finish up with our exercises. We usually do around 10 to 12 exercises for the semester.
And then we go into more of a creative part. So this is when they're developing their entire
collection. They are looking at trend research. They are pulling together design elements and
finishings, fabrication, so they can actually build a collection.
The bullet point list at the top you see is a list in order of a specific sequence that I like to take
with these exercises and what we focus on in these exercises to try and hone in on the
sequence-specific order for their workflow that is the most relevant to their workflow.
Some examples of the exercises we do. So elastic properties and wastepans.
The 3D Pen Tool, for bodycon patterns, a really helpful tool. This is particularly helpful because
not everyone has the right tool that's asking you how to do the best的時候. And not everyone,
Everyone that goes into the CLO program understands patterns fully, and this is a tool that makes
patterns for you just by drawing on the avatar, so this is a very powerful tool.
We also do custom fabrics.
One exercise asks students to create their own maps, their diffuse or color maps and
their normal maps and displacement maps, opacity maps also at some times.
The current final prompt for the semester right now, and we've done a few different
types of final projects, but the current one is called Designing for the Modern Professional,
and what we're trying to do with this is to answer the challenges of modern professionals.
So we're thinking they are working long days.
They need wearability and comfort, but sustainability is always a factor.
That's something that should just be ingrained in everything.
It's built in now, and the other little twist that we put on it because of modern day consumers
and the demands that we have is the challenge of convertibility, so getting them to solve
that problem.
It's a challenge of how you give a consumer multiple styles, a range of styles in a single
garment.
The students are able to choose from two focuses when we go into this final stage, the first
one being a digital direction and the second being a digital, fully digital.
The main difference here between the two, both are going to create and build, design
and build.
The digital will go down a five-look capsule collection, but the digital will go down a
physical garment route, and the digital will go heavier in the video campaign, so animation
rendering, as well as a line sheet and lookbook, potentially even a virtual showroom.
We also like to focus on technology.
We also like to focus on tech packs because that is very industry-relevant.
You're going to need a tech pack for anywhere you go and anything you're doing in fashion,
so tech packs are a great thing to focus on, and it is quite easy nowadays with Closet
being able to generate it for you automatically.
So going into an example of student work, and this is Christian's project.
When he was taking this class, so his final, what we do is have a final slide deck, so
it's like a pitch deck for their entire concept and collection, and we were still on the final
prompt of video games as their inspiration, and this was the video game that Christian
had picked for that semester.
There's a mood board for this.
It's a little bit of a puzzle.
This is his character profile, so explaining this character that all the design decisions
are pretty much centered around, focused on, the concept or ethos, you could say, color,
palette, and fabrication, the lineup of all five looks.
Sometimes not all of them work.
And there are all of these atomic, opal-like combinations that you actually see a lot
of, and the misplacement and distortion of them is a lot.
It's sometimes **** that Persian style and new and my favorite thing to talk about is
cloning the 아 .
It's too clean, very old.
There's probably no cloning device like that, but it's a little more cloning than I think.
Maybe some time tomorrow you can come up with an idea of a cloning thing like that.
Or somebody's going to do that because they're very difficult to do.
Another component of their final project
is to print out full-scale patterns from Clo
and create a physical garment from it.
So one of the things that is something I try to drive home
from the very beginning of the class
is that Clo isn't necessarily a magic tool
for creating garments that are first-time-write samples.
The mesh that we're using in 3D design is really deceptive,
and we have to train our eyes to recognize
that we're not creating a physical garment from it.
We have to train our eyes to recognize that we're not creating a physical garment from it.
We have to train our eyes to recognize areas of fit issues, pretty much.
So you see on the left here a PDF of some patterns of Christians
and the pants that came from them.
And I put in here a few additional garments from other students.
And there are three things that I like to use Clo for
that I wanted to share.
So if your department has specific blocks or slopers that you use,
it is definitely worthwhile to digitize them
and start using those exact slopers in Clo
so that you can work in tandem with your real-world slopers.
Another thing that I find Clo to be particularly amazing for
is exploring and experimenting with these iconic, historic garments
that we otherwise wouldn't have any time with,
let alone being able to touch them and cut into them
and apply new fabrics to them.
So it's a great way for anyone,
but particularly students and young designers,
to explore and learn from these existing garments.
The third thing is to use Clo in my other courses for demonstrations.
For example, tailoring is a really complicated,
and of course, in the jacket we do.
The tailored jacket has a lot of nuance in the pattern drafting.
And I find that if you give the students a comprehensive idea
of what the goal is,
they seem to digest each of the steps a little more easily.
So Clo can definitely be a tool
for just status quo conventional studio demos.
But Clo is also a great tool for students
that are in their early twenties and the early twenties,
who don't have any knowledge of how to do it,
but can also use Clo to create a lot of different things.
So it's a great way to get in touch with your students
and to make sure that they understand Clo.
So lastly, some challenges and solutions.
Clo is a really massive program.
It can be intimidating.
Sometimes you'll have a class that,
it feels like the students almost have impostor syndrome.
Like, they don't have any business being in the program almost. And what helps, in my experience, is that,
in my experience, is to constantly reiterate the core concepts, how the program works,
how the main functions are literally always going to be in the property editor or from a right-click
pop-up menu, as simple as that is. Having written and video tutorials, the students have expressed
how much they use it, specifically from the instructors giving the course for some reason,
because there are a lot of CLO tutorials out there, but if you're talking about exactly what
you're doing in the class and covering that material, I think it's really, really helpful.
And just being able to view it and review it whenever you want.
I also like to reassure the students about midway in the semester, there's always this point where
the program just clicks. And up until that point,
most of the students are going to be able to review it whenever they want.
Most of the students are going to be able to review it whenever they want. And up until that point,
most of the students are feeling really frustrated. They're discouraged because
the program is difficult. They might not be catching on as quickly as other students.
And it's almost always, there's a point where the program just feels more comfortable.
It's like a plateau of learning. And then you feel like you can do anything. You understand
the tools and the functions well enough to do anything you need to do. There are many ways to
achieve the same goal in this program, just like a lot of different softwares. Illustrator and
Photoshop are great examples of this. So if you know that, it's a little bit about solving the
problem in the way that your brain understands it. How does your brain normally solve this
problem? And if you know how to do it in real world, you can likely do it in CLO, just the same.
The technical limitations.
That students might have in this course. It's a large program. It takes a lot of processing power.
When you get to some of the more advanced operations and functions, like animation
specifically, you'll find students have issues with their computer, not being able to handle it,
or full-on crashes of the program. There have been cases of students' computers completely
dying.
As my child is in a myocardial cirrhosis and layer is dying in the middle of the course.
So, if there's a way for the department to have additional computers or a computer lab
set up. That's really really helpful.
I also tell them not to underestimate because this is a classic thing that that students
do. Whether it's the time constraints of other courses during finals.
of animation rendering in 3d but it it takes a an exceptional like an abnormal amount of time
from what you might think to do these animation renders so don't underestimate that
and the third one we talked about this for a second but understanding that the 3d mesh is
just ultra deceptive when you're trying to assess fit in your garments you cannot trust
if a garment looks correct in simulation that you're going to be able to print your patterns
out and it's going to be a well-fitting garment there are lots of steps that you need to take
to ensure you're going to get as close as possible to a first time right sample
okay and i would like to introduce christian
saddle and i'll let you take it away christian all right thank you um hello my name is christian
and i'm a free uh freelance 3d fashion designer and i specialize in sustainable digital design
um just a little bit of a back story i never really expected to be in the fashion industry
at all um i spent a lot of my time just doing a lot of graphic design and then like a little
bit of 3d rendering and like blender and things like that and i would make like um basically
mock-ups of like just t-shirts and hoodies and like i just think they were cool and then
i kind of realized that i wanted to elevate my understanding of fashion
which kind of led me to vcu and through my time there i've learned you know a lot of the basics
fundamentals everything like that and i learned a ton it was amazing um my senior year i enrolled
into the co3 class and that truly just changed the way that i thought about fashion design
and i was like wow this is perfect like 3d design i know a little bit about 3d rendering
let's do it um the software really just allowed me to like just visualize and just have like
unlimited potential when it came to like experimenting and just like being able to
like in real time see what i'm doing and like edit it real time just made a huge difference
i was always really passionate about like sustainability and the department itself
was really big on sustainability i took a sustainable sustainability class
and we learned a lot about just like how much there is in like overproduction and over consumption
and so i really wanted to find a way to like kind of put my foot in that area and see it like
anything that i could do can make a difference but i was feeling a little lost and like i didn't
really know how to incorporate that in my design process but with close 3d it actually really helped
me to kind of like sit back and slow down a little bit without without actually having to like
affect my like deadlines or anything like that
so i was able to completely create like virtual environments print them out and then they
definitely saved me a lot of time in the sampling process and it definitely saved me a lot of money
too which is something that as a student is very crucial for me um i think that just those those
two things in particular definitely just boosted my productivity a lot and um it's definitely not
talked about even with talking to um my peers they're like they always say like oh yeah like
it's expensive and having to buy it every week it definitely saved a lot of money in that in that
aspect um i'm definitely grateful for what close 3d has given to me post grad i was able to start
a career with close 3d i do basically technical design everything i do is within close 3d
i help brands pretty much do visual prototyping and then i help them with their fashion solutions
whether that be they want they need patterns done they need a tech pack done or they need
things just done for merchandising renders and stuff like that close 3d really helps me to
explain to brands how cost effective it can be and how much it can save them on time and money
these are just some of the ways that i help brands again i do 3d design and sampling
so i can quickly create digital garments and i can help them eliminate or reduce the need for physical
and i'm just also just streamlining the design process making things go just a little bit faster
by being able to show them the garments in real time saying like you know i can change seam lines
i can change style lines i can change an entire garment pretty much very quickly and give it to
them in a very quick turnaround this is more pattern making technical design i also do a lot
of like fittings i'll take some of their patterns put it in clo
and then i'll like kind of pinpoint where the garment needs altering or if it needs any
things that they didn't really think about such as like facings and stuff like that
and also with that i do generate the tech packs and i'll spec out the garment
and export it and send it to them so they also can send it out to manufacturers for production
and then of course 3d renders and animations this is where i really i first started doing this
i would just create like really high quality um renders of the garments and i would use uh
not only clo but i would use blender and unreal engine to kind of help uh with um
just more realistic lighting or if i needed to do an entire video
i would use blender and unreal to kind of assist with that and this is really good
for like the marketing material and like their websites and social media i think that's it